Guide to the William J. Higginson Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
William J. Higginson Papers,
1950-2007
Higginson, William J., 1938-2008
27 linear ft. (23 record cartons, 3 flat boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book & Manuscript Library Butler Library, 6th Fl. East, 535 West 114th St., New York, NY. 10027
MS#1468
7351663
The William J. Higginson Papers consist primarily of correspondence with other poets and authors. There is also a sizable amount of Higginson's writings, including his manuscript, The Haiku Handbook: How to Write, Share, and Teach Haiku as well as many poems by both Higginson and his colleagues.
History
William J. Higginson spent over forty years studying traditional Japanese poetry. His interest in this subject led him to publish numerous books and articles on the teaching and writing of Haiku and he became one of the foremost authorities on the collaborative form of poetry writing, renku.
Higginson was born on December 17, 1938 in New York City to parents William J. and Nellie (Roby) Higginson Mackay. He first began studying Japanese at Yale University and discovered haiku at this time. Higginson served in the United States Air Force in the late 1950s, during which he was stationed in Misawa, Japan. He continued studying Japanese poetry throughout his deployment. Some years after his return, he went to college on the G.I. Bill and graduated with honors from Southern Connecticut State University in 1969 with a B.A. in English.
After a short stint teaching, Higginson became a Consultant in Writing and the Teaching of Writing in 1972, a job that he held for the rest of his life. He was a charter member of the Haiku Society of America, which as founded in 1968 and served as President in 1976, as well as the editor and publisher of Haiku Magazine. Other publications include three collections of poetry and haiku and numerous essays in anthologies and reference works. His poems, essays, and translations appear in the following periodicals and journals: American Book Review, Center, Footwork, Frogpond, Imprint (Hong Kong), Madrona, Newsweek Japan, Open Magazine, ProFiles, Shearsman (London), Sparrow, Sun, and Telegram (London).
Higginson has published several books in the field, perhaps the most prominent being The Haiku Handbook: How to Write, Share and Teach Haiku (1985), a book that uses examples, many of which were not previously available, from Japanese and other languages. This was a collaborative effort between Higginson and his wife, poet and author Penny Harter. Unique to the book are teaching tools, such as lesson plans, a reference section, and lists of haiku publishers and magazines. A follow-up book entitled The Haiku Seasons expands on the teaching model and gives a comprehensive history of the form. Higginson also published Wind in the Long Grass, an international anthology of haiku for children.
Higginson was active in several professional organizations, most notably P.E.N. American Center, the Poetry Society of America, the National Writers Union (U.S.), the New Jersey Task Force on Literacy in the Arts, and the Association of New Jersey County Cultural and Historical Agencies.
William J. Higginson died on October 11, 2008 after battling cancer. He is survived by his wife, Penny Harter.
Scope and Content
This collection documents the professional life of poet, translator, and literary historian, William J. Higginson. The bulk of the papers are correspondence and writings. Correspondence consists of letters between Higginson and fellow scholars and poets. The writings include drafts of Higginson's manuscript, The Haiku Handbook, numerous poems, and articles about the history and craft of writing Japanese Poetry. There is also a small amount of photographs, multimedia materials, and ephemera.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series.
Series I: Correspondence, 1966-2007
Series II: Writings by Higginson, 1960-2007
Series III: Writings by Others, undated
Series IV: Subject Files, 1973-2005
Series V: Multimedia, 1970s-1990s
Series VI: Photographs, 1950s-2007
Series VII: Ephemera, 1980s
Subjects
Harter, Penny; Higginson, William J., 1938-2008; Haiku.; Haiku--History and criticism.; Haiku--Technique.; Haiku--Translations into English.; Poetry.; Visual poetry
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Gift of Penny Harter, November, 2008
- Series I: Correspondence, 1966-2007
  Series I hold letters from Higginson's friends and colleagues as well as various Haiku societies and organizations. Often colleagues and admirers would send Higginson various poems that they had written for him to criticize or comment on.
  - General Correspondence (Box 1)
    - undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 2001-2007 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Aldridge, Adele, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Amann, Eric, 1968-1994, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 15 to 16)
  - Andras, Villanyi, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Aoyagi, Fay, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Baldwin, Neil, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Barton, Geri, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Beaudoin, Kenneth, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bihler, Charles Harter, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bostok, Janice, 1974-1986 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Brooks, Randy and Shirley, 1989- 1999 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Brower, Gary, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Brown, Naomi, 1993-1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bull, James, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Calkins, Jean, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Calogoras, Meagan, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Childs, Cyril, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cobb, David, 1991-1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Codrescu, Ian, 1981-1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Cook, Lewis, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Corman, Cid, 1968-1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Cramer, Mark, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Crown, Bonnie, 1982-2004 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Davidson, Agnes, 1975-2001 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Demming, Kristen, 1994-1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Eckerman, Joan, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Evetts, Dee, 1984-1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Forges-Ryan, Sylvia, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Frost, Celestine, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Gates, Larry, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Greeting Cards, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Gurga, Lee, 1990-1999 (Box 2, Folder 21 to 22)
  - Haba, James, 1987-1992 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Hackett, James, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Haiku Southwest, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Harr, Lorraine, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Harter, Penny, 1993-1997 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Hashimoto, Kayoko, 1995-1999 (Box 2, Folder 28 to 29)
  - Heitmeyer, Doris, 1989-1995 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Henderson, Harold, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Harold, Christopher, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Hicks, Helen, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Higginson, Elizabeth, 1985-1991 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Horne, Kimiko, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Hoshino, Tsunchiko, 1989-2004 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Hotham, Gary, 1980-1996 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Jewell, Rhoda de Long, 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Jones, Robert, 1985-1993 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Kacian, James, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Kaneko, Tohta, 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Kanterman, Leroy, 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Kennedy, Bruce, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Kenny, Adele, 1982-1990 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Kerr, Walter, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Keyser, Gustave, 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Kondo Family, 1969-2000, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 47 to 48)
  - Lamb, Elizabeth, 1972-1990, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 49 to 50)
  - Landherr Jr., Ken, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Lee, Jeff, 1997-2004 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Laughlin, James, 1976-1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Lerman, Minna, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Lifshin, Lyn, 1978-1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Little, Geraldine, 1974-1995 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Loose, Gerry, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Luce, Ralph A, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Margeson, June, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Masseron, Julien, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - McClintock, Michael, 1971-2001 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - McGinnis, Tim, 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - McNierney, Michael, 1972-1998 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Miyashita, Emiko, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Moore, Leonard, 1987-1993 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Mormino, Kay T, 1968-1973 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Morris, Ivan, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Nolan, Pat, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Novak, Robert, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - O’Connor, John, 1990-1995 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - O’Donnol, Dion, 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Okada, Ritsuo, 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Okazaki, Tadao, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Olczak, George, 1992-1996 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - O’Williams, Paul, 1972-2000 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Pearce, Anna, 1993-1995 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Petty, Ryan, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Pizzarelli, Alan, 1971-1982 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Polster, Edythe, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Poe, Marian, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Porach, Francine, 1989-1993 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Poulter, Scott, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Pratt, Claire, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Procsal, Gloria, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Ratner, Rochelle, 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Reichhold, Jane, 1989-1993 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Rexroth, Kenneth, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Roan, Carol, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Rogers, Steve, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Rotella, Alexis Kaye, 1981-1990 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Roseliep, Raymond, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Ross, Bruce, 1992-1995 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Rutherford, Anne, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Sakurai, Emiko, 1972-1984 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Sato, Hiro, 1976-1983 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Sato, Kazuo, 1982-1989 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Sato, Ken-ichi, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Shimakawa, Kyoko, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Shirane, Haruo, 1997-2000 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Silverman, Hersch, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Simmons, Carl, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Sommerkamp, Sabine, 1981-1990 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Spiess, Robert, 1982-2000 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Squires, Bonnie, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Stark, Larry, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Stefanile, Felix, 1975-1991 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Stubbs, Kendon, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Takado, Sazuko, 1992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Takahashi, Nobuyuki, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Takeshita, Ryusai, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Tanemura, Kenneth, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Taylor, William J, 1968-1977 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Trumball, Charles, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Uchida, Sono, 1982-1993 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Ueda, Makato, 1972-2001 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Van der Heuvel, Cor, 1971-1998 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Verbeke, Geert, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Virgil, Anita, 1969-1998 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Wakiyama, Katsuo, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Webb, Joyce W., 1968-1975 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Welch, Michael Dylan, 1992-1999 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Warner, Gary, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Wiggin, Larry, 1971-1982 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Wilde, Teruko, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Wills, Marlene and John, 1970-1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Wilmott, Rod, 1989-1994 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Wright, David, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Wyatt, Bill, 1968-1996 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Yagi, Kametaro, 1968-1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Yatsuka, Ishihara, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Young, Virginia, Brady, 1970- 1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series II: Writings, 1960-2007
  Higginson's writings contain research, drafts, and notes for various projects such as Butterfly Dreams, The Haiku Handbook, and The Haiku Seasons. The series also has correspondence relating to the creation of these projects and about Haiku in general, proofs of Haiku Magazine volumes 5-6, and poetry written by Higginson in collaboration with colleagues.
  - Manuscripts
    - Butterfly Dreams
      - Autumn, 2005- 2006 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Correspondence, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Drafts, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Spring, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Summer, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - The Haiku Handbook
      - African Haiku, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Chapters 6-7, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Chapters 8, 9, 11, 16, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Draft 1-1, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Draft 1-2, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Draft 1-3, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Draft 1-4, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Draft 2-1, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Draft 2-2, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - Draft 2-3, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Draft 2-4, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Draft 3, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Dutch Examples, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Glossary, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Modern Examples--French, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Modern Examples--Yugoslavian, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - One-Line Haiku, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Outlines, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Reprints, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Season Words, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Teach Writing, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - The Haiku Seasons--Corrections and Design Notes, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - The Haiku Seasons--Drafts, 1988- 1996 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Ten Years, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Wind in the Long Grass, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Poetry
    - General
      - Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 19 to 20)
      - 1960-1979 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - 1980-1989 (Box 5, Folder 22)
      - 1990-1999 (Box 5, Folder 23)
      - 2000-2007 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Group Poetry, 1976-2004 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Haiku by Hian (Higginson), 1968- 1969 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - "Items," 1982 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - One-Line Haiku, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Sampler, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Santa Fe Haiku, 1992-1994 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - "Twenty-Five Pieces of Now"--Correspondence and Drafts, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - "Twenty-Five Pieces of Now"--Masters, [1968] (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Short Works
    - Undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - 1968-1979 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - 1980-1989 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - 1990-1999 (Box 6, Folder 13 to 14)
    - 2000-2005 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Research and Notes
    - Notebooks, 1985-1990s (Box 6, Folder 16 to 17)
  - Haiku Notes and Book Projects, 1988-2005 (Box 7)
  - Poems, Essays and Writings, undated (Box 8)
- Series III: Writings by Others, undated
  This small series consists of poetry and small essays written by friends and colleagues of Higginson. The bulk of the pieces are undated and in many cases the author is not identified.
  - Haiku and Writings, undated (Box 9)
- Series IV: Subject Files, 1973-2005
  Series IV is comprised of printed material such as pamphlets, awards and certificates. There are also files concerning haiku and renku as well as publishing-related documents.
  - General Files, undated (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous and Pamphlets, undated (Box 11)
  - 1970s (Box 12)
  - 1980s- 1990s (Box 13)
  - 1980s (Box 14)
  - 1990s (Box 15)
  - 2000- 2005 (Box 16)
  - Renku, 1973- 1974 (Box 17)
  - 1990s (Box 18)
  - 1990s- 2000 (Box 19)
  - Publishing Files, 1990s (Box 20)
  - 2001- 2002 (Box 28)
- Series V: Multimedia, 1970s-1990s
  Computer disks with backups of Higginson’s writings and audio recordings of poetry readings are held in this series.
  - Floppy Disks and Other Media (Box 21)
  - Audiotapes and CDs (Box 27)
- Series VI: Photographs, 1950s-2000
  Photographs of Higginson and Penny Harter at various poetry functions both within the United States and Japan are in Series VI. Events documented include the Global Renku Symposium and meetings of the Haiku Society of America. Of interest is a photograph of Allen Ginsburg with poet Anne Waldman from 1979. In addition to the photographs, there are a fair amount of slides and negatives.
  - 1987 (Box 22)
  - Allen Ginsburg and Anne Waldman, 1979 (Box 22)
  - Global Renku Symposium, 2000 (Box 22)
  - Haiku Society of America Cherry Tree (Box 22)
  - Japan, 1990 (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous, (2 Folders) (Box 22)
  - Negatives (Box 22)
  - New York City, 1959 (Box 22)
  - Slides (Box 22)
  - Unidentified Photographs, 1950s and 1990s (Box 22)
- Series VII: Ephemera, 1980s
  Series VII contains a variety of realia including buttons, cards and paper products, prints of artwork, cloth and other textiles. Several scrapbooks documenting Higginson’s trips through Japan in the 1980s are held in this series.
  - Art Prints (Box 22)
  - Buttons (Box 22)
  - Cards and Paper Products (Box 22)
  - Notebook, (2 Folders) (Box 22)
  - Scrapbook, (2 Folders) (Box 22)
  - Scrapbook-- Japan, 1987 (Box 22)
  - Ephemera in flat Boxes, (3 Boxes) (Box 23-25)
  - Scrapbook-- Japan, 1989, (4 Folders) (Box 26)
  - Textiles, (5 Folders) (Box 26)
  - Travel Mementos-- Japan, 1989, (4 Folders) (Box 26)